A great way to start, I think, with my view of simplicity
طريقة رائعة للبدء، كما أعتقد، مع رؤيتي للبساطة
is to take a look at TED. Here you are, understanding why we're here,
هي أن نلقي نظرة على TED. ها أنتم هنا، تفهمون لماذا نحن هنا،
what's going on with no difficulty at all.
تفهمون ما الذي يجري، دون أي صعوبة على الإطلاق.
The best A.I. in the planet would find it complex and confusing,
أفضل عقول الذكاء الاصطناعي في الكوكب ستجد هذا معقدًا ومربكًا،
and my little dog Watson would find it simple and understandable
وكلبي الصغير واتسون سوف يجده بسيطًا ومفهومًا،
but would miss the point.
لكنه لن يدرك المغزى.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He would have a great time.
كان ليستمتع بوقته.
And of course, if you're a speaker here, like Hans Rosling,
وبالطبع، إذا كنتَ متحدثًا هنا، مثل هانز روزلنج،
a speaker finds this complex, tricky. But in Hans Rosling's case,
يجد المتحدث هذا التعقيد صعبًا. ولكن في حالة هانز روزلنج،
he had a secret weapon yesterday,
كان لديه سلاح سري بالأمس،
literally, in his sword swallowing act.
حرفيًا, في عرضه لابتلاع السيوف.
And I must say, I thought of quite a few objects
و يجب أن أقول أنني فكرت في عدة أشياء
that I might try to swallow today and finally gave up on,
من الممكن أن أحاول ابتلاعها اليوم لكني تراجعت في نهاية المطاف --
but he just did it and that was a wonderful thing.
لكنه فعلها وكان ذلك شيئًا رائعًا.
So Puck meant not only are we fools in the pejorative sense,
إذًا بَكْ لم يعنِ فقط أننا حمقى بالمعنى الازدرائي،
but that we're easily fooled. In fact, what Shakespeare
بل إننا ننخدع بسهولة. في الواقع ما كان شكسبير
was pointing out is we go to the theater in order to be fooled,
يشير إليه هو أننا نذهب إلى المسرح ليتم خداعنا،
so we're actually looking forward to it.
إذًا نحن فعلًا نتطلع إلى ذلك.
We go to magic shows in order to be fooled.
نذهب للعروض السحرية ليتم خداعنا.
And this makes many things fun, but it makes it difficult to actually
وهذا يجعل الكثير من الأشياء ممتعة، ولكنه يجعل من الصعب في الواقع
get any kind of picture on the world we live in or on ourselves.
أن نكوّن أي صورة عن العالم الذي نعيش فيه، أو عن أنفسنا.
And our friend, Betty Edwards,
و صديقتنا بيتي إدواردز
the "Drawing on the Right Side of the Brain" lady, shows these two tables
السيدة المعنية بالرسم خلال الجزء الأيمن من الدماغ، تعرض هاتين الطاولتين
to her drawing class and says,
لصف الرسم خاصتها وتقول،
"The problem you have with learning to draw
مشكلتكم مع تعلم الرسم
is not that you can't move your hand,
هي ليست أنكم لا تستطيعون تحريك أيديكم،
but that the way your brain perceives images is faulty.
بل أن الطريقة التي تدرك بها أدمغتكم الصور هي طريقة خاطئة.
It's trying to perceive images into objects
فهي تحاول إدراك الصور كأشياء
rather than seeing what's there."
بدلًا من رؤية ما هو موجود هناك.
And to prove it, she says, "The exact size and shape of these tabletops
و لتثبت ذلك، تقول، فإن حجم و شكل أسطح المناضد هذه
is the same, and I'm going to prove it to you."
متماثلة تمامًا، وسأثبت لكم ذلك.
She does this with cardboard, but since I have
هي تفعل ذلك بالورق المقوى، ولكن بما أنني أملك
an expensive computer here
حاسوبًا غالي الثمن هنا،
I'll just rotate this little guy around and ...
سأقوم فقط بلف هذا الصغير و...
Now having seen that -- and I've seen it hundreds of times,
الآن بما أننا رأينا هذا -- ولقد رأيته أنا مئات المرات،
because I use this in every talk I give -- I still can't see
لأنني أستخدم هذا في كل محاضرة ألقيها -- لازلت لا أستطيع أن أرى
that they're the same size and shape, and I doubt that you can either.
أنها ذات الحجم والشكل نفسه، وأشك أنكم تستطيعون فعل ذلك أيضًا
So what do artists do? Well, what artists do is to measure.
اذا ماذا يفعل الرسامون؟ حسنا، إنهم يقوموا بالقياس
They measure very, very carefully.
إنهم يقيسون بحذر شديد.
And if you measure very, very carefully with a stiff arm and a straight edge,
و إذا قمت بالقياس، بحذر و دقه شديدين، و بيد ثابته ، و حواف مستقيمه
you'll see that those two shapes are
سترى أن هذين الشكلين
exactly the same size.
هما نفس الشكل تماما.
And the Talmud saw this a long time ago, saying,
و التلمود رأى هذا منذ وقت طويل فقال،
"We see things not as they are, but as we are."
اننا نرى الأشياء ليست كما هي، بل كما نحن نراها.
I certainly would like to know what happened to the person
أود فعلا أن أعرف ماذا حدث لهذا الشخص
who had that insight back then,
الذي كانت لديه هذه البصيره في ذلك الوقت،
if they actually followed it to its ultimate conclusion.
اذا اتبعوها ليحصلوا على الإستنتاج النهائي
So if the world is not as it seems and we see things as we are,
إذا كان العالم ليس كما يبدو و نحن نرى الأشياء كما نريد
then what we call reality is a kind of hallucination
اذا ما ندعوه بالواقع هو مجرد هلوسه
happening inside here. It's a waking dream,
تحدث داخلنا. إنه حلم يقظه.
and understanding that that is what we actually exist in
و مفهوم لمكان وجودنا
is one of the biggest epistemological barriers in human history.
هو أحد أكبر عقبات نظريات المعرفه في التاريخ الإنساني
And what that means: "simple and understandable"
و ان ما تعنيه : " سهل و مفهوم "
might not be actually simple or understandable,
قد لا يكون سهلا أو مفهوما
and things we think are "complex" might be made simple and understandable.
و الأشياء التي نعتقد انها معقده من الممكن ان نجعلها سهله و مفهومه
Somehow we have to understand ourselves to get around our flaws.
بشكل ما يجب أن نفهم أنفسنا لنتخطى عيوبنا.
We can think of ourselves as kind of a noisy channel.
من الممكن أن نرى أنفسنا كقنوات مشوشة.
The way I think of it is, we can't learn to see
و كما أرى الأمر، لا يمكن أن نتعلم الرؤيه
until we admit we're blind.
حتى نقر بأننا عميان.
Once you start down at this very humble level,
ما أن تبدأ في هذا المستوى المتواضع جدا،
then you can start finding ways to see things.
عندها يمكن أن تبدأ بإبجاد طرق لرؤية الأشياء.
And what's happened, over the last 400 years in particular,
وما حدث خلال الأربعمائة عام السابقه على التحديد
is that human beings have invented "brainlets" --
هو ان البشر اخترعوا قطع الدماغ:
little additional parts for our brain --
قطع إضافية صغيرة لدماغنا،
made out of powerful ideas that help us
جاءت بأفكار قويه لتساعدنا
see the world in different ways.
على رؤية العالم بطرق مختلفه.
And these are in the form of sensory apparatus --
و هي على أشكال حسيه
telescopes, microscopes -- reasoning apparatus --
التلسكوبات , المجاهر - أجزاء منطقيه،
various ways of thinking -- and, most importantly,
طرق متعدده للتفكير، والأهم،
in the ability to change perspective on things.
القدره على تغيير مفهومنا للأشياء.
I'll talk about that a little bit.
سأتحدث عن هذا قليلا.
It's this change in perspective
هو ذلك التغيير في المفهوم،
on what it is we think we're perceiving
وما هو الذي نعتقد أننا نراه
that has helped us make more progress in the last 400 years
الذي ساعدنا على التقدم خلال الأربعمئة سنه الماضية
than we have in the rest of human history.
أكثر مما تقدمنا في بقية التاريخ.
And yet, it is not taught in any K through 12 curriculum in America that I'm aware of.
وحتى الان لم يتم تدريسها فى أى من المقررات الدراسية الاثنا عشر فى امريكا على حد علمي.
So one of the things that goes from simple to complex
لذا فأحد الأشياء التى تتحول من البسيط الى المعقد
is when we do more. We like more.
هو عندما نقوم بالمزيد فنحن نحب المزيد.
If we do more in a kind of a stupid way,
عندما نفعل المزيد بطريقة غبية،
the simplicity gets complex
البساطة تتحول الى التعقيد.
and, in fact, we can keep on doing it for a very long time.
والحقيقة، يمكننا أن نفعل ذلك لمدة طويلة.
But Murray Gell-Mann yesterday talked about emergent properties;
ولكن مورى جالامان تحدث عن الخصائص الناشئة البارحة.
another name for them could be "architecture"
والتي يمكن ان يطلق عليها ايضا " الفن المعماري "
as a metaphor for taking the same old material
كاستعارة لاخذ المواد القديمة نفسها
and thinking about non-obvious, non-simple ways of combining it.
والتفكير بطرق غير الطرق الواضحة والبسيطة لتجميعها معا.
And in fact, what Murray was talking about yesterday in the fractal beauty of nature --
وفى الحقيقة، ماكان يتحدث عنة مورى حول الجمال الجزئى للطبيعة،
of having the descriptions
بامتلاك وصفات
at various levels be rather similar --
على نواح مختلفة متشابهة،
all goes down to the idea that the elementary particles
كله يعود إلى فكرة أن الجزيئات الاولية
are both sticky and standoffish,
ملتصقة و تباعدية في ذات الوقت
and they're in violent motion.
وفى حالة حركة عنيفة.
Those three things give rise to all the different levels
تلك الأشياء الثلاثة تمثل على كل المستويات
of what seem to be complexity in our world.
لما يبدو أنه التعقيد في عالمنا.
But how simple?
لكن ما مدى البساطة؟
So, when I saw Roslings' Gapminder stuff a few years ago,
لذا عندما رأيت أعمال روزلينج جاميندر منذ عدة سنوات،
I just thought it was the greatest thing I'd seen
اعتقدت أنها اعظم فكرة قد رأيتها
in conveying complex ideas simply.
فى تبسيط الأفكار المعقدة.
But then I had a thought of, "Boy, maybe it's too simple."
ولكن عندها راودتنى فكرة أنها قد تكون بسيطة أكثر من اللازم.
And I put some effort in to try and check
وقمت ببعض الجهد لكى أحاول وأتأكد
to see how well these simple portrayals of trends over time
من أجل فهم إلى أي مدى لهذه الاتجاهات من التصورات البسيطة خلال الوقت
actually matched up with some ideas and investigations from the side,
أن تتطابق واقعيا مع بعض الافكار والبحوث في هذا الجانب،
and I found that they matched up very well.
ووجدت أنها تتطابق بشكل جيد.
So the Roslings have been able to do simplicity
إذا تمكن الروزلينج من الوصول للبساطة
without removing what's important about the data.
من دون التخلي عن المهم في المعلومات.
Whereas the film yesterday that we saw
في حين أن الفلم الذي شاهدناه البارحة
of the simulation of the inside of a cell,
الذي يحاكي الجزء الداخلي لخلية،
as a former molecular biologist, I didn't like that at all.
كعالم سابق في الأحياء الذرية، لم يعجبني ذلك أبداً.
Not because it wasn't beautiful or anything,
ليس لأنه لم يكن جميلاً أو شيئا من هذا القبيل
but because it misses the thing that most students fail to understand
بل لأنه يغفل الشيء الذي لا يفهمه أكثرية الطلبة
about molecular biology, and that is:
عن الأحياء الذرية، وهو أن
why is there any probability at all of two complex shapes
لماذا هناك أية احتمالية على الإطلاق لشكلين معقدين
finding each other just the right way
بأن يجدا بعضهما بالطريقة الصحيحة تماماً
so they combine together and be catalyzed?
بحيث يندمجا معاً ويتم تحفيزهما؟
And what we saw yesterday was
وما رأيناه البارحة هو أن،
every reaction was fortuitous;
كل تفاعل حدث بمحض الصدفة.
they just swooped in the air and bound, and something happened.
فقد انطلقوا في الهواء فقط ثم ارتبطوا وحدث شيء ما.
But in fact, those molecules are spinning at the rate of
لكن في الواقع تلك الذرات تدور بسرعة
about a million revolutions per second;
مليون دورة في الثانية تقريباً.
they're agitating back and forth their size every two nanoseconds;
فهي تهتز إلى الأمام والخلف بقدر حجمها كل نانو ثانيتين.
they're completely crowded together, they're jammed,
فهي محتشدة مع بعضها احتشاداً كاملاً. ومحشورة،
they're bashing up against each other.
وتضرب ببعضها البعض.
And if you don't understand that in your mental model of this stuff,
وإن لم تكن تفهمها كذلك في تصورك الذهني لهذه الأشياء،
what happens inside of a cell seems completely mysterious and fortuitous,
فما يحدث داخل خلية سيبدو شديد الغموض وخاضعاً للصدفة.
and I think that's exactly the wrong image
وأعتقد أن هذه الصورة خاطئة تماماً
for when you're trying to teach science.
إن كنت تحاول أن تدرس العلوم.
So, another thing that we do is to confuse adult sophistication
إذا شئ آخر نرتكبه هو أن نخلط بين نزعة التكلف عند الراشدين
with the actual understanding of some principle.
وبين الفهم الحقيقي لمبدأ ما.
So a kid who's 14 in high school
إذاً فطفل ذو ١٤ عاماً في الثانوية
gets this version of the Pythagorean theorem,
يعطى هذه النسخة من نظرية فيثاغورس،
which is a truly subtle and interesting proof,
وهو إثبات مصقول وجدير بالاهتمام حقاً،
but in fact it's not a good way to start learning about mathematics.
ولكنه في الواقع ليس طريقة جيدة للبدء في تعلم الرياضيات.
So a more direct one, one that gives you more of the feeling of math,
إذاً فإثبات مباشر كهذا، الذي يعطيك إحساساً أكثر بالرياضيات،
is something closer to Pythagoras' own proof, which goes like this:
هو شيئ أقرب لإثبات فيثاغورس نفسه والذي يجري بهذا الشكل.
so here we have this triangle, and if we surround that C square with
إذاً هنا لدينا هذا المثلث، وإن أحطنا المربع سي "C"
three more triangles and we copy that,
بثلاث مثلثات أخرى ونسخنا ذلك،
notice that we can move those triangles down like this.
لاحظوا أنه بإمكاننا تحريك تلك المثلثات إلى الأسفل هكذا،
And that leaves two open areas that are kind of suspicious ...
وذلك يترك لنا مساحتين مفتوحتين تبدوان مشبوهتان قليلا،
and bingo. That is all you have to do.
وإليكم ذلك. ذلك كل ما عليكم فعله.
And this kind of proof is the kind of proof
وهذا النوع من الإثباتات هو النوع
that you need to learn when you're learning mathematics
الذي تحتاج تعلمه حين تتعلم الرياضيات
in order to get an idea of what it means
حتى تُكون فكرة عن ما تعنيه
before you look into the, literally, 1,200 or 1,500 proofs
قبل أن تبحث في البراهين الاثنا عشر أو الألف والخمسمائة
of Pythagoras' theorem that have been discovered.
لنظرية فيثاغورس التي تم اكتشافها.
Now let's go to young children.
والآن دعونا نذهب إلى الأطفال الصغار.
This is a very unusual teacher
هذه معلمة غير تقليدية أبداً
who was a kindergarten and first-grade teacher,
كانت معلمة لرياض الأطفال وللصف الأول،
but was a natural mathematician.
لكنها عالمة رياضيات بالفطرة.
So she was like that jazz musician friend you have who never studied music
هي مثل ذلك الصديق عازف موسيقي الجاز والذي لم يدرس الموسيقى أبداً،
but is a terrific musician;
لكنه موسيقي رائع.
she just had a feeling for math.
لديها مجرد إحساس بالرياضيات.
And here are her six-year-olds,
وإليكم طلابها ذو الست أعوام،
and she's got them making shapes out of a shape.
فقد جعلتهم يصنعون شكلا هندسيا من شكل هندسي آخر.
So they pick a shape they like -- like a diamond, or a square,
إذاً يقومون باختيار الشكل الذي يروقهم، معين أو مربع،
or a triangle, or a trapezoid -- and then they try and make
أو مثلث أو شبه المنحرف--ثم يحاولون صنع
the next larger shape of that same shape, and the next larger shape.
الشكل الأكبر من الشكل ذاته، ثم الشكل الأكبر وهكذا.
You can see the trapezoids are a little challenging there.
ويمكنكم رؤية أن أشكال شبه المنحرف تشكل تحدياً بعض الشيء.
And what this teacher did on every project
وما قامت به هذه المعلمة في كل نشاط من نوعه
was to have the children act like first it was a creative arts project,
هو أن تدع الأطفال يشعرون بأنه مشروع فني في البدء
and then something like science.
وبعد ذلك بأنه شيء من العلوم.
So they had created these artifacts.
إذاً فقد صنعوا تلك الأشكال الفنية.
Now she had them look at them and do this ... laborious,
الآن تدعهم ينظرون إليها ويقومون بذلك الجهد--
which I thought for a long time, until she explained to me was
والذي اعتقدت لفترة طويلة، وحتى شرحت لي أنه
to slow them down so they'll think.
لإمهالهم حتى يفكرون.
So they're cutting out the little pieces of cardboard here
إذاً فهم يقصون قطع الكرتون الصغيرة هنا،
and pasting them up.
ويلصقونها معاً.
But the whole point of this thing is
لكن الهدف من العمل ككل هو
for them to look at this chart and fill it out.
أن ينظروا إلى هذا الجدول ويقوموا بتعبئته.
"What have you noticed about what you did?"
ثم يتم سؤالهم "مالذي لاحظتموه حول ما صنعتم؟"
And so six-year-old Lauren there noticed that the first one took one,
وبالنسبة للورين ذات الست أعوام فقد لاحظت أن أول شكل أخذ واحد فقط،
and the second one took three more
والثاني أخذ ثلاثة زيادة،
and the total was four on that one,
والمجموع كان أربعة لتلك.
the third one took five more and the total was nine on that one,
والثالث أخذ خمسة زيادة، والمجموع كان تسعة لتلك،
and then the next one.
ومن ثم الذي يليه.
She saw right away that the additional tiles that you had to add
إذا فقد رأت مباشرة أن القصاصات الزائدة التي عليها أن تزيدها
around the edges was always going to grow by two,
حول الأطراف ستزداد باثنتان دوماً.
so she was very confident about how she made those numbers there.
إذا فقد كانت واثقة بكيفية توصلها لتلك الأرقام هناك.
And she could see that these were the square numbers up until about six,
ويمكنها رؤية أن تلك الأعداد تربيعية وحتى العدد ستة تقريباً.
where she wasn't sure what six times six was
حيث لم تكن متأكدة ما هي نتيجة ضرب ستة في ستة،
and what seven times seven was,
وما هي نتيجة ضرب سبعة في سبعة.
but then she was confident again.
ولكنها كانت واثقة.
So that's what Lauren did.
إذاً هذا ما فعلته لورين.
And then the teacher, Gillian Ishijima, had the kids
وبعد ذلك قامت المعلمة، جيليان إشجيما، بجعل الأطفال
bring all of their projects up to the front of the room and put them on the floor,
يجلبون كل أعمالهم إلى مقدمة الغرفة ووضعها على الأرض.
and everybody went batshit: "Holy shit! They're the same!"
ووقف الجميع مذهولين. يا إلهي! كلها متشابهة!
No matter what the shapes were, the growth law is the same.
أياً كانت الأشكال فقانون النمو-الازدياد هو ذاته.
And the mathematicians and scientists in the crowd
وسيتعرف أساتذة العلوم والرياضيات في هذا الجمهور
will recognize these two progressions
على هاتين المتواليتين
as a first-order discrete differential equation
كمعادلة تفاضلية منفردة من المرتبة الأولى،
and a second-order discrete differential equation,
ومعادلة تفاضلية منفردة من المرتبة الثانية.
derived by six-year-olds.
تم استنباطهما من قبل أطفال في السادسة.
Well, that's pretty amazing.
هذا حقاً مدهش.
That isn't what we usually try to teach six-year-olds.
ليس هذا ما نحاول أن نعلم الأطفال في السادسة من عمرهم عادةً.
So, let's take a look now at how we might use the computer for some of this.
إذاً فلننظر الآن كيف يمكننا استعمال الكمبيوتر في بعض من هذا.
And so the first idea here is
والفكرة الأولى هنا هي
just to show you the kind of things that children do.
فقط أن أعرض لكم الأشياء التي يمكن للأطفال القيام بها.
I'm using the software that we're putting on the $100 laptop.
أنا استعمل البرنامج الذي وضعناه في الكمبيوتر المحمول ذو المائة دولار.
So I'd like to draw a little car here --
إذاً أريد أن أرسم سيارة صغيرة هنا.
I'll just do this very quickly -- and put a big tire on him.
سأفعل ذلك سريعاً. وأضع دواليب كبيرة عليها.
And I get a little object here and I can look inside this object,
وسأحضر شيئا صغيرا هنا، ويمكنني أن أرى داخل هذا الشيء.
I'll call it a car. And here's a little behavior: car forward.
سأسميه سيارة. وهنا القليل من الحركة فتتقدم السيارة.
Each time I click it, car turn.
في كل مرة أنقر، تلف السيارة.
If I want to make a little script to do this over and over again,
سأقوم بكتابة بعض الأوامر لتكرار تلك الحركة مرة بعد مرة.
I just drag these guys out and set them going.
فقط أقوم بسحب هؤلاء لأدعهم ينطلقون.
And I can try steering the car here by ...
ويمكنني أن أحاول توجيه السيارة هنا من خلال-
See the car turn by five here?
رأيتم السيارة تنحرف بقدر خمسة هنا؟
So what if I click this down to zero?
وماذا إذا نقرت حتى تصل الصفر؟
It goes straight. That's a big revelation for nine-year-olds.
إنها تمشي بخط مستقيم. هذا نوع من الاكتشاف العظيم بالنسبة لأطفال التاسعة من العمر.
Make it go in the other direction.
دعوها تذهب في الاتجاه الآخر.
But of course, that's a little bit like kissing your sister
ولكن طبعاً ذلك يشبه تقبيل أختك قليلاً
as far as driving a car,
فيما يخص قيادة السيارة.
so the kids want to do a steering wheel;
إذا يريد الأطفال مقود للسيارة.
so they draw a steering wheel.
فيرسمون مقوداً للسيارة.
And we'll call this a wheel.
وسنسمي هذا مقوداً.
See this wheel's heading here?
وهل ترون عنوان المقود هنا؟
If I turn this wheel, you can see that number over there going minus and positive.
عندما أدير المقود، يمكنكم وؤية ذلك العدد هناك يصبح سالباً وموجباً.
That's kind of an invitation to pick up this name of
هذا نوع من الدعوة للتعرف على أسماء
those numbers coming out there
تلك الأعداد التي تظهر هناك
and to just drop it into the script here,
وأضيف ذلك إلى سلسلة الأوامر هنا.
and now I can steer the car with the steering wheel.
والآن يمكنني قيادة السيارة باستعمال المقود.
And it's interesting.
وذلك حقاً ممتع.
You know how much trouble the children have with variables,
تعرفون مدى الصعوبة التي يواجهها الأطفال مع المتغيرات،
but by learning it this way, in a situated fashion,
ولكن من خلال تعلمها بهذه الطريقة، بوضعها في قالب قائم،
they never forget from this single trial
لن ينسوا أبداً من هذه التجربة الواحدة
what a variable is and how to use it.
ماهو المتغير وكيف يمكن استخدامه.
And we can reflect here the way Gillian Ishijima did.
ويمكننا التفكير هنا بنفس طريقة جيليان إشجيما.
So if you look at the little script here,
إذاً إن نظرتم إلى سسلسة الأوامر هنا،
the speed is always going to be 30.
فالسرعة ستكون ثلاثين دائماً.
We're going to move the car according to that over and over again.
وسنقوم بتحريك السيارة وفقاً لذلك مرة بعد أخرى.
And I'm dropping a little dot for each one of these things;
وسأضع نقاطاً لكل من هؤلاء.
they're evenly spaced because they're 30 apart.
تتباعد النقاط بصورة متساوية لأن بين كل منها ٣٠.
And what if I do this progression that the six-year-olds did
وماذا إذا طبقت هذه المصفوفة التي توصل إليها أطفال السادسة من العمر
of saying, "OK, I'm going to increase the speed by two each time,
إذا سأقول نعم، سأضاعف السرعة مرتين في كل مرة
and then I'm going to increase the distance by the speed each time?
ومن ثم سأزيد المسافة حسب السرعة في كل مرة؟
What do I get there?"
مالذي أحصل عليه هنا؟
We get a visual pattern of what these nine-year-olds called acceleration.
نحصل على صورة لما يسميه ذو التاسعة من العمر التسارع.
So how do the children do science?
إذاً كيف يدرس الأطفال العلوم؟
(Video) Teacher: [Choose] objects that you think will fall to the Earth at the same time.
(حوار غير واضح)
Student 1: Ooh, this is nice.
الطفل : هذا رائع
Teacher: Do not pay any attention
المدرس : لا تعر اهتماماً
to what anybody else is doing.
لاي شيء يحدث من حولك
Who's got the apple?
فقط من حصل على التفاحة ؟
Alan Kay: They've got little stopwatches.
آلان كي : لديهم عدادات وقت
Student 2: What did you get? What did you get?
المدرس : مالذي حصلت عليه .. مالذي حصلت عليه ؟
AK: Stopwatches aren't accurate enough.
آلان كي : يبدو ان عدادات الوقت ليست دقيقة بما فيه الكفاية
Student 3: 0.99 seconds.
الفتاة : 0.99 ثانية
Teacher: So put "sponge ball" ...
المدرس : اذا ضع " كرة اسفنجية "
Student 4l: [I decided to] do the shot put and the sponge ball
الفتاة : لقد كان هناك طلقة وكرة اسفنجية
because they're two totally different weights,
لانهما مختلفين تماما بالاوزان
and if you drop them at the same time,
واذا رميتهم بنفس الوقت
maybe they'll drop at the same speed.
ربما سيقعان بنفس السرعة
Teacher: Drop. Class: Whoa!
المدرس : ارمهما
AK: So obviously, Aristotle never asked a child
إذا من الواضح أن أرسطو لم يسأل طفلاً أبداً
about this particular point
عن هذه النقطة بالتحديد،
because, of course, he didn't bother doing the experiment,
لأنه بالطبع لم يتكبد عناء القيام بالتجربة،
and neither did St. Thomas Aquinas.
ولم يقم بها القس، توماس أكويناس كذلك.
And it was not until Galileo actually did it
ولم يكن حتى قام جاليليو بها في الواقع
that an adult thought like a child,
أن فكر شخص راشد كالأطفال.
only 400 years ago.
مجرد أنه كان قبل ٤٠٠ سنة.
We get one child like that about every classroom of 30 kids
نحن لدينا على طفل واحد فقط في اي صف من أصل ٣٠ طفلاً
who will actually cut straight to the chase.
والذي يمكنه الوصول إلى الفكرة المطلوبة مباشرة.
Now, what if we want to look at this more closely?
الآن، ماذا إذا أردنا أن ننظر إلى ذلك نظرة أقرب؟
We can take a movie of what's going on,
يمكننا أن نرى شريطاً مصوراً عما يحدث،
but even if we single stepped this movie,
لكن حتى وإن أبطأنا الشريط
it's tricky to see what's going on.
فإنه من الصعب مشاهدة ما الذي يجري.
And so what we can do is we can lay out the frames side by side
إذا ما يمكننا فعله هو أن نضع الأطر جنبا لجنب،
or stack them up.
أو نصفها فوق بعضها.
So when the children see this, they say, "Ah! Acceleration,"
حيث حين يراها الأطفال يقولون، "نعم، التسارع،"
remembering back four months when they did their cars sideways,
وسيتذكرون قبل أربعة أشهر عندما قامو بتحريك سياراتهم إلى اليمين واليسار.
and they start measuring to find out what kind of acceleration it is.
وسيبدأون بالقياس لمعرفة أي نوع من التسارع هو.
So what I'm doing is measuring from the bottom of one image
وبالتالي ما أفعله هو القياس من أسفل أحد الصور
to the bottom of the next image, about a fifth of a second later,
إلى أسفل الصورة التي تليها، وبعد ما يقارب خمس الثانية
like that. And they're getting faster and faster each time,
هكذا، ويصبحون أسرع وأسرع في كل مرة.
and if I stack these guys up, then we see the differences; the increase
وإن وضعتهم تحت بعضهم، فسنرى الفروق، الازدياد
in the speed is constant.
في السرعة ثابت.
And they say, "Oh, yeah. Constant acceleration.
فسيقولون، آه نعم، التسارع الثابت.
We've done that already."
لقد قمنا به.
And how shall we look and verify that we actually have it?
وكيف لنا أن ننظر ونتأكد أن لدينا في الواقع؟
So you can't tell much from just making the ball drop there,
لا يمكننا أن نقول الكثير من مجرد جعل الكرة تقع هناك،
but if we drop the ball and run the movie at the same time,
لكن إن أوقعنا الكرة وشغلنا الشريط المصور بذات الوقت،
we can see that we have come up with an accurate physical model.
يمكننا أن نرى أننا توصلنا إلى نموذج حركي دقيق.
Galileo, by the way, did this very cleverly
قام جاليليو بذلك، بالمناسبة، بذكاء
by running a ball backwards down the strings of his lute.
وذلك بدحرجة كرة إلي الخلف على أوتار العود.
I pulled out those apples to remind myself to tell you that
قد أخرجت تلك التفاحات لأذكر نفسي لأقول لكم أن
this is actually probably a Newton and the apple type story,
هذه في الواقع قد تكون قصة من نوع نيوتن والتفاحة،
but it's a great story.
لكنها قصة رائعة.
And I thought I would do just one thing
وفكرت أن أقوم بشيء واحد فقط
on the $100 laptop here just to prove that this stuff works here.
على جهاز اللابتوب ذو المائة دولار هنا فقط لأثبت أن هذه الأفكار تعمل هنا.
So once you have gravity, here's this --
إذاً مجرد أن حصلتم على الجاذبية، إليكم التالي--
increase the speed by something,
ضاعف السرعة بعامل،
increase the ship's speed.
ضاعف سرعة السفينة.
If I start the little game here that the kids have done,
إذا بدأت اللعبة الصغيرة التي صنعها الأطفال هنا،
it'll crash the space ship.
ستؤدي بسفينة الفضاء للاصدام.
But if I oppose gravity, here we go ... Oops!
لكن إن قمت بمحاربة الجاذبية، ها نحن ننطلق--أووه!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
One more.
مرة أخرى.
Yeah, there we go. Yeah, OK?
نعم، ها نحن. حسناً؟
I guess the best way to end this is with two quotes:
اعتقد أن أفضل طريقة لإنهاء الحديث هي باقتباسين.
Marshall McLuhan said,
قال مارشال مكلوهان،
"Children are the messages that we send to the future,"
"الأطفال هم الرسائل التي نرسلها للمستقبل."
but in fact, if you think of it,
لكن في الواقع، إن فكرتم بها،
children are the future we send to the future.
الأطفال هم المستقبل الذي نرسله للمستقبل.
Forget about messages;
دعوكم من الرسائل.
children are the future,
الأطفال هم المستقبل.
and children in the first and second world
والأطفال في العالم المتقدم وشبه المتقدم ،
and, most especially, in the third world
والأخص في العالم النامي ،
need mentors.
يحتاجون إلى مرشدين.
And this summer, we're going to build five million of these $100 laptops,
وفي هذا الصيف سنصنع ٥ ملايين من أجهزة اللابتوب ذات المائة دولار
and maybe 50 million next year.
وربما ٥٠ مليون في العام القادم.
But we couldn't create 1,000 new teachers this summer to save our life.
ولكننا لا نستطيع أن نصنع ألف معلم جديد هذا الصيف وإن كان ذلك حيوي لإنقاذ حياتنا.
That means that we, once again, have a thing where we can put technology out,
وهذا يعني أنه أصبح لدينا مرة أخرى شيئا يمكننا استخدام التكنولوجيا فيه.
but the mentoring that is required to go
ولكن الإرشاد يتطلب
from a simple new iChat instant messaging system
نظام محادثة (تشات) جديد بسيط
to something with depth is missing.
إلى شيء أعمق ينقصنا.
I believe this has to be done with a new kind of user interface,
اعتقد أن ذلك يجب أن يطبق باستخدام واجهة استخدام جديدة من نوعها
and this new kind of user interface could be done
ويمكن لواجهة المستخدم الجديدة تلك أن تصنع
with an expenditure of about 100 million dollars.
بمبلغ يقارب المائة مليون دولار.
It sounds like a lot, but it is literally 18 minutes of what we're spending in Iraq --
يبدو أنه مبلغ كبير، لكنها تعادل حقاً ١٨ دقيقة مما نصرفه في حرب العراق.
we're spending 8 billion dollars a month; 18 minutes is 100 million dollars --
نحن نصرف ٨ بلايين دولار شهرياً. ١٨ دقيقة هي ١٠٠ مليون دولار.
so this is actually cheap.
إذاً فهذا رخيص في الواقع.
And Einstein said,
وقال إينشتاين،
"Things should be as simple as possible, but not simpler."
يجب أن تكون الأشياء بسيطة بقدر الإمكان ، ولكن ليست اكثر سذاجة.
Thank you.
شكراً.